外海 世界上最广袤无垠的荒芜之地
The world's greatest wilderness, the open ocean.
海洋占了地球表面的二分之一以上
It covers over half the surface of our planet.
这里没有藏身之处 食物也寥寥无几
Here, there is nowhere to hide and little to eat.
这海洋如同一片沙漠
It's the marine equivalent of a desert.
飞旋海豚在这片海洋里巡查
And patrolling this desert, spinner dolphins.
它们成群结队
They stick together
数量多达5000
in a super-pod, 5,000 strong.
成群出动大大提高了它们的捕食几率
That maximises their chances of finding something to eat.
和生活在海里的其他生物一样
Like all who live here, they
它们必须使出浑身解数
must go to extraordinary length
才能立足于这片汪洋大海
To make their home in the big blue.
这片空旷的海域里很少能检测到生命的迹象
There are rare moments when these empty seas can explore with life.
哥斯达黎加太平洋海岸的灯鱼
Lanternfish, off the pacific coast of costa rica.
和(垂钓时所用的)假饵差不多大
They're scarcely bigger than minnows,
虽然他们体积小 但是他们数量庞大
But what they lack in size they make up for in numbers.
无论在哪儿 它们都是数量庞大的鱼群
They are one of the most numerous fish anywhere.
通常它们只有在晚上才会到海面寻找浮游生物充饥
Normally, they only come to the surface at night to feed on plankton,
但现在它们却在白天游上了海面
But this immense shoal has risen during the day,
几乎可以肯定 它们是为了产卵
Almost certainly in order to spawn.
对于海豚来说 这是一个千载难逢的机会
For the dolphins, this would be a bonanza.
它们利用回声来确定鱼群的位置
They have located the shoal using their echo-sounding calls.
但它们得加快行动
But they have to get to it quickly.
因为别的捕食者也在蠢蠢欲动
They are not the only hunters here.
黄鳍金枪鱼发现了这个灯鱼鱼群
Yellowfin tuna have also detected the shoal.
而它们身后
And behind them,
是翼展两米的魔鬼鱼
with their two-metre wingspans, mobula rays
现在 海洋里的速度担当 旗鱼
Now sailfish, one of the fastest fish in the sea,
也加入了这场捕食的行列
Have joined the chase.
灯鱼随时都会回到深海
The lanternfish may return to the deep at any moment.
但现在海豚已经到达战场
But now the dolphins have got here.
他们游到鱼群的下方 将鱼群逼回海面
They swim beneath the shoal, pinning it to the surface
并迫使鱼群逐渐缩小
And forcing the lanternfish to pack more closely together.
大海开始沸腾了
And now the sea begins to boil.
金枪鱼以每小时40多英里的速度冲入灯鱼群
The tuna charge into the shoal at over 40mph.
游得最慢的魔鬼鱼也到达了战场
The slower-swimming rays arrive at last.
它们张大嘴巴
With their immense mouths agape,
将数百条灯笼鱼吞入腹中
They scoop up the lanternfish by the hundred.
大部分鱼群已被冲散
The shoal has now been largely dispersed,
旗鱼在短短十五分钟内
And the sailfish pick off the survivors.
解决了余下的幸存者
In just 15 minutes,
如今仅剩下银色鱼鳞随波逐流
All that's left is a silvery confetti of scales.
但在这里 如此盛宴难得一遇
But here, such feasts are only too infrequent.
海豚表现出了极大的忍耐力
Whilst the dolphins perform great feats of endurance,
而其余的生物走向了极端
Others are driven to even greater extremes
只为了在这荒漠般的海洋里觅食
To find food in this ocean desert.
一个沉睡的巨人
A sleeping giant.
抹香鲸
A sperm whale.
这个家族正在为下一次捕食养精蓄锐
This family is resting between bouts of feeding.
没人知道这个拥有世界上最大脑袋的生物在做什么梦
Who knows what the owners of the biggest brain in the planet dream about.
这头抹香鲸有个幼崽
One has a calf.
它已经两周岁大了
It's about two weeks old
但还需要母乳喂养
but still dependent on its mother's milk.
它饥肠辘辘
It's hungry.
它利用嘀嗒声来和它的妈妈交流
It communicates with its mother using a pattern of clicks.
但它的妈妈依旧在沉睡
But its mother slumbers on.
小抹香鲸的身上都是吸盘鱼
The calf, covered in sucker fish,
它没法把身上的鱼除掉
of which it can't yet rid itself
所以小抹香鲸要耐心等待
Has to be patient.
鲸鱼抹香鲸睡醒以后神清气爽 继续前行
Sleep over and refreshed, the whales move on.
抹香鲸等不及它们的猎物浮出水面
Sperm whales don't wait for their prey to rise themselves.
于是他们决定潜入深海去寻找
They swim down into the depths to find it.
它们做了一连串的深呼吸
They take a series of heavy breaths
给血液充满氧气
..to saturate their blood with oxygen.
接着向深海游去
Then down they go.
这个抹香鲸家族一起潜入水中寻找乌贼
This entire family dives together in search of squid.
抹香鲸妈妈用尽全身力气向下游
A mother will push her body to the limits of her endurance,
显然它的幼崽有点跟不上它
And already it's hard for her calf to keep up with her.
幼崽竭尽全力靠近妈妈
The calf sticks to its mother as closely as it can
时不时碰碰妈妈 似乎是在寻求安慰
touching her frequently, as if for reassurance.
但是下潜300米深以后
But 300 metres down,
小抹香鲸似乎再也憋不住气了
It seems the calf can't hold its breath any longer.
在长大以前 小抹香鲸不能参加捕猎活动
In their early years, calves are forced to sit out the hunt.
而那些成年抹香鲸继续下潜
The adults continue their dive.
抹香鲸妈妈的嘀嗒声
The mother changes her calls
逐渐变得响亮而急促
Into a series of louder and more rapid clicks.
它正在用声呐搜索成群的乌贼
She's now using sonar to hunt down shoals of squid.
在800米深处 一阵嘀嗒声响起
At 800 metres, a burst of clicks.
接着一片沉寂
Then silence.
她抓到了
She's made a catch.
整个过程长达1小时
that could be way for as much as an hour.
终于 妈妈满载一肚子的乌贼
Finally, the mother returns from the deep
从深海游回来了
with a stomach full of squid.
等了许久 这只小抹香鲸终于可以喝上奶了
After a long wait, this hungry calf can take some milk.
抹香鲸是哺乳动物中产奶量最丰富的
It's one of the richest produced by any mammal,
因此小抹香鲸可以一整天大快朵颐
And the calf guzzles a bathful of it a day.
这些幼崽要花六年的时间
It may be six years before a calf
才能学会深海潜水
masters the art of deep diving
并且独立捕食
And is able to find food for itself.
这片汪洋的空旷
The emptiness of the big blue is
造就了捕食者的艰难处境
what makes life so hard for hunters.
但也正是这空旷
But it's this emptiness
给予了猎物一隅安全的栖息地
that makes it comparatively safe for prey.
一只破壳没几天的海龟宝宝
A baby turtle, hatched just days ago，
正在远离海岸附近这片
is leaving the crowded
拥挤而又危险的水域
Dangerous waters of the coast
朝着外海前行
and heading for the open ocean
直到近几年我们才破解了
Only recently have we begun to solve
海龟宝宝在成年前
The mystery of where baby turtles
去了哪里的谜团
disappear to in their early years.
最初 它们靠植物填饱他们的小肚子
To start with, they fill their little stomach with plants
但很快它们就需要更管饱的食物
But soon they need something more substantial.
每片海域离岸数百英里的地方
Hundreds of miles offshore, in every ocean,
都有许多未谙世事的幼崽
There are communities of young castaways.
漂浮着的任何东西都会吸引它们
So anything that floats attracts them.
一根浮木
A log.
这原木大概已经在海上漂了好几年了
It may have been at sea for several years,
并且已经成了这些小群体的中心了
And it has already become the centre of a small community.
小河豚也是为了这个来到这里
Young puffer fish are here for the same reason.
这根浮木就像一个避难所
A floating log is just the kind of refuge
也正是这只小海龟一直在寻找的
This young turtle has been looking for.
这里不仅有海藻可以吃
Here, there's not only seaweed on which to graze,
还有藤壶
but barnacles
不过学会躲藏才是至关重要的
But it's important to stay under cover.
一条年轻的丝鲨也漂洋过海来到这里
A young ocean-going silky shark is here, too.
它正在学习分辨什么好吃
It's learning what tastes good.
什么不好吃
And what doesn't.
现在我们知道许多小海龟都会在这样的地方待上好多年
We now know that many young turtles stay in such places for several years,
直到它们长大成年
until adulthood.
即使这意味着它需要独当一面
Even if it means facing the full force of the high seas.
阳光洒在海上
The sun beating down on the deep blue
提高了海面的温度 促进了海水的蒸发
Warms the surface waters so that they evaporate.
当水蒸气上升时 便凝结成了云
As the vapour rises, it condenses into clouds.
很快风起云涌
They rapidly build into gigantic, burgeoning towers,
最终形成风暴
Which eventually generate violent storms,
有的甚至可以覆盖1000英里的区域
some 1,000 miles across
飓风席卷广阔的海面
Hurricane-force winds sweep across the open ocean,
掀起30多米高的巨浪
Building waves that can rise to 30 metres tall.
在这里 船只会沉入大海 销声匿迹
Out here, ships have been known to sink without trace.
每年有1.3亿集装箱
130 million containers are shipped
装运后横跨大洋
across the oceans every year
然而平均每天就有4个集装箱沉入大海
And on average, four of them fall into the sea every day.
1992年 几个装运着
In 1992, a few were lost
洗澡玩具的集装箱沉入了大海
That contained a consignment of bath toys...
集装箱里装着7000只像这样的塑料鸭
..including 7,000 plastic ducks like these.
它们从阿拉斯加出发 开始了长达1000英里的旅程
They started their travels 1,000 miles off alaska.
有的飘过了太平洋
Some drifted right across the pacific
最终到达澳大利亚
ocean and reached australia.
还有的一路北漂
Others were carried north
停留在俄罗斯和阿拉斯加之间的海岸上
And landed on shores between Russia and Alaska.
更有甚者到达了北极圈
They even found their way into the high Arctic.
有一只洗澡鸭在海上漂流了15年
One duck, having been at sea for 15 years
横跨了三个大洋
And crossing three oceans,
最终到达了苏格兰西海岸
Eventually landed on the west coast of Scotland.
它们的行迹生动地向我们展示了
Their travels vividly illustrate how a network of currents
洋流是如何将各个海洋连成一体
connects all our oceans into one
成为一个巨大的循环系统
gigantic circulatory system
汪洋大海里的许多生物
Many of the inhabitants of the big blue
都依赖洋流
rely on these currents
来找到食物充饥
To carry them to feeding grounds.
一头大青鲨
The blue shark.
它靠着宽大的翼形鱼鳍
It travels over 5,000 miles a year,
顺着洋流
Riding on the currents,
每年游经5000多英里
supported by its broad wing-shaped fins
这头大青鲨大概两个月没有进食了
This one may not have eaten for two months.
不过洋流能带来几英里外
But the currents can carry promising traces of fatty oils
丰厚油脂的的味道 并指引着它前行
from many miles away and will lead it to its next meal.
经过几天的跋涉 食物的味道越来越近
After days of travel, the smell of food gets stronger.
一头被船撞死的鲸
A dead whale, recently struck by a ship.
这堪比一顿饕餮盛宴
This could be a real feast,
不过大青鲨需要小心谨慎
But the blue shark must be cautious.
一条大白鲨
Great white sharks
体重是大青鲨的十倍
ten times heavier than a blue
对这头鲸鱼的尸体也蠢蠢欲动
are highly possessive around a whale carcass.
大白鲨迫不及待地吃起了高能量的鲸脂
Great whites are eager to feed on energy-rich whale blubber,
现在我们知道了这是它们的主要食物
Which we now know forms a major part of their diet.
一旦大白鲨吃饱喝足
Once the great white has had its fill,
小型鲨鱼 例如大青鲨
Smaller sharks, like the blue shark,
就会吃剩下的尸体
tackle what's left of the carcass
随着死鲸身上油脂味道的扩散
As the oils from this dead whale spread more widely,
越来越多的大青鲨被吸引过来
More and more blue sharks appear.
不出几日 尸体上的鲸脂就会被吃光抹尽
Within days, the carcass will be stripped of its blubber.
失去了油脂维持浮力
Then, no longer kept buoyant by its oil,
这头鲸将尸沉深海
It will sink into the depths below.
而这条补充了脂肪储备的大青鲨
The blue, with its reserves of fat replenished,
可以两个月不再进食了
Can now survive for another two months without eating.
深海中一半以上的生物
Over half of all animals in the
都随洋流前进
open ocean drift in currents
水母可以横跨一整个大洋
Jellyfish cross entire oceans
缠上它们触角的任何东西都会沦为它们的盘中餐
Feeding on whatever happens to tangle with their tentacles.
有的水母可以长达1米甚至2米
Some can grow to a metre, even two metres, across.
幸运的时候
And when, by lucky chance,
会遇到一片浮游生物
They encounter a patch of sea rich in plankton,
它们的数量剧增
Their numbers explode.
这是一个明智之举
It's such a successful strategy
腔肠动物是地球上
That jellies are one of the most
最常见的生命形态之一
common life form on the planet
不过腔肠动物中 有种和水母很像
But among the jellies, and looking somewhat like them,
但比水母更为复杂和危险的生物
Is a rather more complex and sinister creature.
那就是葡萄牙军舰水母
The Portuguese Man o' War
它靠气囊漂浮在水中
It floats with the help of a gas-filled bladder,
顶部是一个垂直的薄膜
Topped by a vertical membrane.
像船帆一样
With that serving as a sail,
在激流中维持平衡
It maintains a steady course through the waves.
气囊下的长触须
Long threads trail behind it,
可以长达30米
some as much as  30 metres long.
每根触须上都有成千上万的刺细胞
Each is armed with many thousands of stinging cells.
一根触须就可以杀死一条鱼
A single tentacle could kill a fish
少数案例中还能杀死一个人
or, in rare cases a human
潜藏在这些剧毒触手周围的
But among its lethal tentacles
是一只以啃食僧帽水母刺细胞为目的的军舰鱼
Lurks a man-o'-war fish that feeds by nibbling them.
虽然这条鱼对水母的毒性有些许免疫
Whilst this fish has some resistance to the stings,
但它仍须万分谨慎
It must still be extremely careful.
大多数鱼则没有这么幸运了
Most other fish are not so lucky.
一根触手抓住了这条鱼 再收"钓线"把鱼拖近
A tentacle has caught this one and reels it in.
它已经被麻痹了
It's already paralysed.
特殊的肌肉触手将猎物带到其他部位
Specialised muscular tentacles transfer the victim to others
逐渐消化猎物
That digest the catch,
通过化学物质液化它
liquefying it with parsal chemicals
最终这条鱼只剩下
Eventually, all that is left
鱼皮和鱼鳞
is a scaly husk.
这个如饥似渴的葡萄牙军舰水母
This voracious man-o'-war
一天可以吃掉一百多条小鱼
May collect over 100 small fish in a day.
放眼望去 汪洋大海似乎平淡无奇
For the most part, the big blue seems featureless
是个微风拂过 不受陆地影响的地方
a place where the winds blow, uninterrupted by land.
但是海面之下有绵延不绝的山脉
But beneath the surface there are long mountain ranges,
深海沟和孤立的火山山峰
Deep trenches and isolated volcanic peaks
大海比人眼所见更深不可测
That make it far more varied than the human eye can see.
我们也仅仅在细节中发现
We are only just discovering in any detail
深海生物是如何探索汪洋的
How the inhabitants of the big blue exploit that.
一头孤独的鲸鲨正开始着一段特殊的旅途
A lonely whale shark on a special journey.
她和一架小型飞机差不多长
She is as long as a small aircraft
重达20多吨
and she weighs over 20 tons
和许多鲨鱼一样
Like many sharks,
她是卵胎生而不是单纯的卵生
she does not lay eggs but gives birth to life.
她鼓鼓的肚子里有300个小生命
She carries up to 300 of them in her swollen belly.
她应该是海洋里最大的鱼类
She may be the biggest fish in the sea,
但是鲸鲨产仔的地方
But the place where whale sharks
至今还没有找到
give birth has not yet been found.
然而 今天 我们可能
Today, however, we may be a step
离解开这个谜团又近了一步
closer to solving this mystery.
我们知道大量的鲸鲨
We have known that great numbers of whale sharks,
在每年的特定时间
At certain times of the year,
会在加拉帕戈斯群岛附近出现
appear around the Galapagos Islands.
它们会聚集在一个
Here they assemble around a tiny island,
突然从深海里升起的小岛周围
That rises abruptly from particularly deep water.
该岛被称为达尔文岛
It's known as darwin island.
在这里 翻腾的洋流带来了深海里的营养物质
Here, swirling currents bring up nutrients from the deep,
这片水域因此变得如此丰饶
So enriching these waters
以至于吸引了大量来自四面八方的鱼类
that they attract great concentrations of fish from far and wide.
数以千计的双髻鲨也聚集在这里
Thousands of hammerhead sharks also assemble here.
它们几乎都是雌性
They are nearly all female.
它们似乎也是来这里繁衍后代的
They, too, it seems, have come here to breed.
鲸鲨受到了特别的欢迎
The whale shark receives an extraordinary welcome.
丝鲨 有三米之长
Silky sharks, themselves three metres long,
在它粗糙的皮肤上弹跳
Bounce against her rough skin...
也许是为了刮掉它们身上可能有的寄生虫
..perhaps to scrape off any parasites they might have.
这些鲨鱼对于任何新生鱼崽都是一种威胁
These sharks could be a danger to any newly born young.
所以可能为了避开它们
So, perhaps to avoid them,
鲸鲨选择下潜
The whale shark dives...
直至600米深的水域
..down to around 600 metres.
在那里产下它的孩子
And there she may release her young.
在深海里
In these great depths,
远离那些在上层水域掠食的捕食者
Away from the predators that hunt in the waters above,
还有丰富的食物
And with abundant food,
她的幼崽能在离开父母前茁壮成长
Her babies could grow and eventually disperse.
没有人
No-one, it is true,
在这人迹罕至的深海里见到过小鲸鲨
Has ever seen young ones in these little-visited depths.
但事实上 每年都会有成千上万只待产的鲸鲨来到这里
But the fact that hundreds of expectant whale sharks come here every year
有确凿的证据表明
Is strong evidence that somewhere here
这儿的某处是海里最大的育儿室
Lies the nursery of the biggest fish in the sea.
世界上有近3万座大规模岛屿
There are almost 30,000 sizeable islands
散布在海洋里
Scattered across the world's oceans.
其中一个是南乔治亚岛
One of them is south georgia...
对于那些为了繁殖被迫降落的海洋居民来说
..an ideal place for those ocean dwellers
这里是一个理想的地方
Who are compelled to land in order to breed.
比如四处漂泊的信天翁
The wandering albatross.
它们可能一年都在海面上飞翔
It may spend as much as a year continuously at sea.
寻找食物
Searching for food,
翼展3.5米宽
Gliding on wings that are 3.5 metres across
信天翁是现存最大的鸟类
The biggest of any living bird.
全世界有一万六千只信天翁
The entire world population of 16,000 wanderers
会在南乔治亚岛筑巢
Nest on south Georgia
还有就是其他位于南太平洋
And half a dozen or so of the other smaller islands
一些较小的岛屿
That lie in the southern ocean.
现在是春天 这只鸟又回到了
It's spring and this bird is returning
自己以前筑的巢
To the nest site it's always used.
它的终身伴侣已经在这里恭候多时了
Its lifelong partner is already here.
在南乔治亚岛
In south georgia,
个别鸟的一生都在被观察研究
Individual birds have been studied for their entire lives,
研究表明 年老的一对在它们三十多岁的时候
Revealing that older pairs, in their late 30s,
还会不遗余力地为它们的孩子
Will go to extraordinary lengths to give their young
提供最好的人生开端
The best possible start in life.
这只雏鸟现在已经几周大了
This chick is now several weeks old,
但温暖的绒毛还没有掉
But still has its warm, downy coat.
这只雏鸟需要母亲反刍鱼和乌贼来实现定期喂养
The chick will need a regular supply of regurgitated  fish and squid,
在外海 食物如此稀少
With food so scarce in the open ocean,
父母双方都要在几千平方英里的范围内寻找
Both parents may have to scour thousands of square miles
只是为了提供一顿饭
Just to provide enough for one meal.
年迈的父母在南极的冬日里苦苦挣扎
Ageing parents struggle on all through the antarctic winter
只为抚养出一只强壮 健康的后代
To raise a chick that is big, strong and healthy.
130天之后
After some 130 days,
雏鸟开始
The youngster begins to replace
长出适用于飞翔的羽毛
its down with flight feathers.
历经九月 它们的下一代终于长大成年
Finally, nine months after their egg was laid,
这只雏鸟准备离开了
This chick is ready to leave.
近些年它们抚养的雏鸟中
Of all the chicks they've reared in recent years,
像这样被悉心照料的雏鸟才最有可能存活下来
Such a favoured chick will have the best chance of survival.
但这也将是它们最后一次
But it will also be their last.
年迈的父母再也不会从它们努力付出中恢复过来
Elderly parents never recover from their exertions.
它们很快就会离开这座岛 再也不会出现
They will soon leave this island, never to be seen again.
在外海中幸存
Surviving in the open ocean
一直考验着海洋生物的极限
Has always tested animals to the limit...
但今天它们将面临另一个新的威胁
..but today they face a new additional threat.
塑料
Plastic.
一百多年前
Just over 100 years ago,
我们发明了一个奇妙的新材料
We invented a wonderful new material
它可以被塑造成各种形状
That could be moulded into all kinds of shapes
我们花了很大力气
And we took great trouble to
来确保它耐磨
ensure that it was hard-wearing,
耐腐蚀和坚不可摧
Rot-proof and virtually indestructible.
现在 每年
Now, every year,
我们将大约800万吨的垃圾倾倒入大海
We dump around eight million tonnes of it into the sea.
这些会将大量的海洋生物
Here, it entangles and drowns
紧紧缠住并致死
vast numbers of marine creatures.
但它的影响会更广
But it has even more widespread
更深远
and far-reaching consequence.
一群短鳍领航鲸
A pod of short-finned pilot whales.
它们生活在一起 也许
They live together in what are, perhaps,
这是整个海洋里最紧密的家族
The most closely knit of families in the whole ocean.
今天 在大西洋的欧洲海域 和其他地方一样
Today, in the atlantic waters off europe, as elsewhere,
它们也受到了塑料的威胁
They have to share the ocean with plastic.
一个母亲带着自己的新生儿
A mother is holding her newborn young.
但孩子已经死了
It's dead.
它不舍得撒手
She is reluctant to let it go
已经带着死去的孩子很多天了
And has been carrying it around for many days.
塑料分解后
As plastic breaks down,
会和其他污染物结合
It combines with these other pollutants
被大量的海洋生物消吸收
That are consumed by vast numbers of marine creatures.
像这样的高等捕食者
In top predators like these,
工业化学品会带来致命的后果
Industrial chemicals can build up to lethal levels...
它的幼崽可能是被
It's possible her calf may have been poisoned
自己受到污染的母乳毒害了
By her own contaminated milk.
领航鲸脑容量很大
Pilot whales have big brains.
它们当然会体会到情感
They can certainly experience emotions.
从成年鲸的行为来判断
Judging from the behaviour of the adults,
失去幼儿会影响到整个家庭
The loss of the infant has affected the entire family.
除非世界上塑料流动和工业污染对世界海洋的污染减少
Unless the flow of plastics and industrial pollution into the world's oceans is reduced,
在未来的几个世纪里
Marine life will be poisoned by them
海洋生物都将会被毒害
for many centuries to come,
生活在汪洋大海里的生物
The creatures that live in the big blue
可能比地球上任何动物
are perhaps more remote
搬家的次数都要多
than any animals on the planet.
但如果要避免人类对它们的影响
But not remote enough, it seems,
他们搬得似乎还不够远
To escape the effects of what we are doing to their world.
在浩瀚的海洋里
The biggest challenge of filming
拍摄最大的挑战是
in the vastness in the open ocean.
寻找你的目标
Is to find your subject...
蓝色星球摄制组想要拍摄
..and the blue planet team wanted to film
其中一件最难拍的东西
One of the most elusive of them all,
就是极少被目击到的 沸腾的海洋
The rarely witnessed "boiling sea".
直到现在 这种海豚集群进食的场景
Until now, this feeding frenzy
仍然具有传奇色彩
has been the stuff of legends.
在澳大利亚东北部
After some promising sightings off
有人声称看见过这种场景
the north-east cost of Australia
于是摄制组开始着手调查
The team heads out to investigate.
我们知道这事无比非凡 我们知道就在那儿
We know it's a phenomenon, we know it's out there,
科学家们有文件记录过
The scientists have documented it,
渔民告诉了我们
The fishermen have told us about it,
所以我们知道肯定会出现 但是没人会疯狂到
So we know it's happening, but no-one has been crazy enough
试着去那里
To attempt to go out there and
拍下这些画面 除了我们
actually film it, except for us
摄制组开始在太平洋上
The team start their search 100
100英里的海域进行搜索
miles out in the pacific ocean
之所以叫 沸腾的海洋 是因为金枪鱼
The reason it's called a "boiling sea" is that the tuna
从水下冲上来
Are actually coming out of the water
袭击灯鱼群
And attacking lanternfish and it
溅起了白色的浪花
creates a lot of white water
为了拍摄沸腾的海洋
To film the boiling seas,
摄制组必须先找到一大群饵鱼
The team must first find a large shoal of bait fish,
很可能就是
Most likely to be lanternfish
晚上浮出水面产卵的灯鱼
Rising to the surface at night to spawn.
几天之后
A few days out,
艾德里安认为她可能在
Adrian thinks he may have spotted a
回声探测器上发现一个巨大的鱼群
giant shoal on the echo sounder
我们看到是是一个非常 非常密集的层次
What we're seeing is a very, very dense layer
大约在200米深的地方
At about 200 metres' water depth.
因此 这所表明的事实是
And so, the fact that we've got this would suggest
我们发现了一个非常深且密集的鱼群
That we have a very deep and dense layer of fish.
在辽阔海洋中拍摄的最好的方法之一
One of the best ways to film at such depths in the open ocean
就是使用水下机器人
Is to use an rov - a remotely operated vehicle -
带上感光摄像机
Carrying a light-sensitive camera.
但在外海上使用这样的重型设备
But working with such heavy equipment in the high seas
是一项危险的操作
Is a risky operation.
幸运的是 有一组技术人员在场
Fortunately, a team of technicians is on hand,
24小时之后 他们准备重新启动
And 24 hours later, they're ready to relaunch.
艾德里安把他们的希望
Adrian drops them on top
放在一大群灯鱼上
Of what he hopes is a large shoal of lanternfish.
好消息是 我们放机器人下去
Good news is, we've just put the rov down,
直到到250米深的地方
We're down at 250 metres,
这是电缆能延伸到的最远距离了
Which means we've gone to almost the end of the cable
没有东西爆炸飞所以我们继续工作
And nothing's blown up so we're back in business.
但是这儿什么都没有
But there's almost nothing there,
只有很薄一层的浮游生物
Just a thick layer of plankton.
在接下来的三个星期里
Over the next three weeks,
他们一只灯鱼都没发现
They don't find a single lanternfish.
这次拍摄是我们对海洋
This trip is the perfect illustration
知之甚少的完美例证
Of why we know so little about the ocean
我们出来找东西
We came out looking for something,
我们不停地搜寻 搜寻 搜寻
We've searched and searched and searched,
最后还是没有找到
And we still haven't found it
即使你想尽了所有办法
Even with every single tool you could wish for.
事实表明 摄制组正在拍摄时
As it turned out, the team had been filming
出现了厄尔尼诺现象
At the very start of el nino
这是一种不可预测的异常气候现象
An unpredictable climatic event
海洋温度突然上升
When sea temperatures can suddenly rise
破坏了鱼类的产卵行为
And disrupt the spawning behaviour of fish.
十八个月之后 情况才会好转
It would be 18 months before conditions would improve
摄制组才能继续他们的探索
And the team could continue their quest.
太平洋的另一边 哥斯达黎加
The other side of the pacific ocean, off costa rica.
这次 不是寻找猎物
This time, rather than searching for their prey,
摄制组在寻找它们的猎手
The team are looking for their predators.
但在无尽的蓝色海洋中
But in the endless blue,
即使寻找一大群海豚也不容易
Even finding a massive pod of dolphins isn't easy.
离岸20英里 系列制片人马克 布朗洛
20 miles offshore, series producer mark brownlow
带领了一个空中拍摄团队
Leads an aerial filming team
观测数千平方英里的海洋
Scanning thousands of square miles of ocean...
但没发现一只海豚
..but there's not a dolphin in sight.
三天了 没发现飞旋海豚
Day three, no spinner dolphins.
开始有点担忧了
Getting worried now...
最终 在辽阔的海洋搜寻十天之后
Finally, after ten days on the open ocean,
他们得到了回报
They get their reward.
是的 海豚
Ok, dolphins!
喔喔
Woohoo!
太棒了
Yes!
飞旋海豚
Spinners!
看到海豚后 潜水组
With dolphins in sight, the dive
开始拦截它们
team race to intercept them.
看 飞旋海豚
Spinners, look!
原计划是拍摄海豚
The plan is to film the dolphins'
在水下的疯狂进食
feeding frenzy from under water.
几百只海豚在这个地方跳来跳去
Several hundred dolphins jumping all over the place,
看起来是这样的
It looks like this could be it.
他们追上海豚
They catch up with the dolphins.
但是他们晚了一步
But they're too late.
啊 天啊
Ah, dear.
什么都拍到吗 罗杰 什么都没有
Nothing, rog? just...nothing.
只有鱼鳞和鱼骨
Just fish scales and bones,
就是在一场战役中
It's like turning up at a battle
看到所有的尸体被遗弃一样
Just to see all the dead bodies left over.
为了有机会拍摄海豚进食
To stand a chance of filming the dolphins' feeding,
水下拍摄组需要更加主动
The dive team need to be more proactive.
蕾切尔搭顺风车 在水下跟着它们
Rachel hitches a ride, following them underwater,
寻找它们下次进食的任何线索
Searching for any clue to where they might go next.
最终 搜寻三周之后
Finally, after three weeks of searching,
水下拍摄组捕捉到一个巨大的进食场面
The dive team catch a huge feeding event,
一个巨大的灯鱼群
A massive shoal of lanternfish
被好几百只飞旋海豚包围
Being rounded up by hundreds of spinner dolphins.
场面精彩纷呈
That was incredibly intense.
一个非常大的鱼饵球
A very large bait ball
大概有一个足球场那么大
Spread over probably the size of a football field.
就这样在你的肩膀 头顶来回穿梭
Things coming in and over your shoulder, over your head,
真是不可思议
It was incredible.
第一次
For the first time,
空中摄制组可以记录下这种壮观场面
The aerial team can record the epic scale of this spectacle.
我们听说过沸腾海洋的故事
You know, we heard these stories of boiling seas,
没想到这是真的
this is real
这么大规模
They're huge.
在浩瀚的海洋荒野里
The vastness of the ocean wilderness
捕捉这样一非凡事件是一个极大的挑战
Made capturing this extraordinary event a great challenge.
但这就是给我们的奖励
But this is the reward,
一场在汪洋大海里
A moment of unparalleled drama
无与伦比的视觉盛宴
In the immense expanse of the big blue.
下次 我们将踏上富饶的绿色海洋之旅
Next time, we journey into the bountiful green sea.
这些都是魔法世界 奇异生物的家园
These are enchanted worlds, home to strange creatures...
只有最机灵的生物才能获得胜利
..where only the most ingenious will triumph.
解说：大卫·爱登堡
Translated by
MAGGIE & BUNNY
翻译：马子尾 & 兔子
Supervised by
VERONICA
监制：斑斑
Proofreaded by
CSARDAS & WILDER
校对：达斯 & 歪二德
Compressed by
DREAM TEAVELER
压制：失梦旅行
Effected by
WILDER FROM SOU
特效：歪二德
奥兰·多尔蒂
制片人
阿德里安弗林
海洋生物学家
罗杰芒斯
水下摄影师
汤斯维尔
2014年10月份
通讯信号丢失
马克·布朗洛
系列制片人
蕾切尔·巴特勒
导演
汪  洋  大  海
蓝 色 星 球 Ⅱ 幕 后
蓝色星球Ⅱ
(学名长吻原海豚 因跳出水面后能以体轴为中心旋转数次再入水而得名"飞旋海豚")
(灯鱼可以反射出闪烁的光芒 被誉为"会游泳的宝石")
(Minnow泛指鲤科小型鱼类 假饵"米诺"为常用路亚假饵种类)
(学名蝠鲼 最早出现于中生代侏罗纪时期)
(旗鱼:海洋中游速最快的鱼类之一 时速可达110英里)
(吸盘鱼:学名印鱼 吸盘由背鳍变化而来 摄食其载送者的食物残渣或体外寄生物)
(学名僧帽水母 形似水母 但其实是一个包含水螅体及水母体的群落)
(军舰鱼:又称僧帽水母鱼,和僧帽水母是共栖关系 这种关系仅对军舰鱼有利 而对于水母一方却没有好处)
(雌性鲸鲨会将卵留在身体内 直到幼鲨生长到40至60厘米后才释出体外)
(1835年26岁的查尔斯·达尔文是首位踏上这块土地的科学家)
(此为生物富集现象 即食物链中营养级别越高的生物,体内残留的毒物越多)